Alright, as Michael has caught me up to speed, we're in the
middle of a discussion of what happens when a woman starts selling
off properties. She's in the unenviable situation of being dependent on the
heirs of her late husband, usually not her children in the situation
we're discussing,
to get her food and eventually her כתובה. Ketubah. And apparently they're
not doing their job, and so at a certain point she starts
selling off fields that belong to them in order to make sure
that she can live.
So I'm going to start actually at the very first line, last
word, כיצד, Keitzad, דף צ"ז עמוד א'. Daf Tzadik Zayin Amud Aleph.
כיצד מוכרת, Keitzad mocheret, how does she sell? What's going on here
in the case where she sells? How does it all work out?
Because it's a little complicated. As soon as she gets remarried, her
right to getting sustenance from the heirs immediately disappears. So if
she sells their land in order to get sustenance, but she then
gets married, say the next month or something like that, she's immediately
going to lose that right to sustenance. The heirs are then going
to go back to the person who bought the land and say,
"Oh no no, we need this land, this land actually belongs to
us, you didn't have the right to buy it." Actually it's going
to be a whole mess. So how does it exactly work? אמר
רב דניאל בר רב קטינא. Amar Rav Daniel bar Rav Katina. Interesting,
there are certain names that appear very rarely in the תלמוד, Talmud,
Daniel is one of them. We'll see one more that's sort of
interesting.
I've never heard of this guy.
She's
selling fields that she did not bring into the estate?
That's correct. She's selling fields that come from her husband's estate,
which might have been used to pay a כתובה. Ketubah. עיקר כתובה,
Ikar Ketubah, could
have been used to pay כתובה, Ketubah, could have been used to
support the יורשים, Yorshim, it's fields that belong to her husband's estate.
המוכרת, Hamocheret, so she sells. Okay, that's right. אמר רב דניאל בר
רב קטינא אמר רב הונא. Amar Rav Daniel bar Rav Katina amar
Rav Huna. So we may not have heard of him, but we
know who he is. He is somebody from the generation, two generations
after רב, Rav, so sort of somewhere in the middle of the
time of the אמוראים. Amoraim. His teacher apparently is רב הונא, Rav
Huna, who is ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva of סורא. Sura. And
he says as follows: מוכרת
אחת לשנים עשר חודש ולוקח מפרנס אחת לשלושים יום ורב יהודה אמר
מוכרת לשישה חודשים ולוקח מפרנס אחת לשלושים יום. Mocheret achat lishneim asar
chodesh velokeach mefarnes achat lishloshim yom verav Yehuda amar mocheret
lishisha chodashim velokeach mefarnes achat lishloshim yom. There's a מחלוקת machloket about
exactly how long she sells, but essentially she sells enough land to
prepare herself for
so that she will be sustained for the extent of a year,
that's the position of רב הונא. Rav Huna. And then what happens
is that she actually gets the money in monthly installments. Installments? Yes,
something like that. The reason being that as soon as she no
longer has the right to this sustenance, to these מזונות, mezonot,
the יורשים, yorshim, the heirs are going to swoop in and take
this land back from the person who has purchased it. So right
now they are essentially paying a kind of rent for the benefit
of the land. They continue to pay her her sustenance, and once
she has gone through a year's worth of sustenance, then that land
becomes entirely the property of the people who bought it.
So she's selling, you know, even just for a year, meaning
she's selling not necessarily the largest fields there, because a field's worth
you don't usually buy a field for a year.
The point that's not clear is exactly how long she's selling for.
But apparently she has there is a way to determine that she
is selling properties that will sustain her for a year. I mean,
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda has an even more conservative position. רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda says she only sells enough to sustain her for six
months at a time and she only gets paid
one month at a time.
תניא כוותיה דרב הונא מוכרת לשנים עשר חודש ולוקח מפרנס אחת לשלושים
יום תניא כוותיה דרב יהודה מוכרת לשישה חודשים ולוקח מפרנס אחת לשלושים
יום.
Tanya kavatei deRav Huna mocheret lishneim asar chodesh velokeach mefarnes achat lishloshim
yom tanya kavatei deRav Yehuda
mocheret lishisha chodashim velokeach mefarnes achat lishloshim yom. So we have two
ברייתות baraitot that seem to support. So for certain to try to
figure out who's the authoritative view, it's a challenge. Who exactly is
in charge?
Really it's a rental.
It's a rental until... But it's a rental where you're actually making
payments on the each rental payment.
It's like the furniture payment installment plan.
Something like that, right? You are, you're paying for the הנאה hana'ah
of the field until such time as the end of the payment
comes along, at which point you own the entire field.
Is that clear, Avrum? Yeah, except why does Rashi
say when she gets married then the field goes back to the
יורשים? yorshim?
Well, that's the whole point, is that because they have an estate,
if they—Yeah. It doesn't go back to the יורשים yorshim if they've
already paid off the entire—the entire price of the field. It only
goes back if she gets married in the middle. It's necessary—look at
what Rashi says exactly.
Rashi says שאם תינשא יחזיר מה שבידו ליורשים. she'im tinasei yachazir mah
shebeyado leyorshim.
Which—which דיבור המתחיל dibur hamaschil are you looking at?
הלוקח לא ימסור לכל המעות. haloke'ach lo yimsor lechol hama'os. Okay, hold
on, ומזונות של חודש בחודש שאם תינשא יחזיר מה שבידו
ליורשים.
umezonos shel
chodesh bechodesh she'im tinasei yachazir mah shebeyado leyorshim. Right.
So what does that mean כל המעות, kol hama'os, right? He has
some sense of כל המעות. kol hama'os. כל המעות kol hama'os is
what it would cost him to buy the field outright. Right? And
they say: why doesn't he—why doesn't he buy it outright? Because it's
going to get very complicated. If he gives her the entire sum
of money and then she ends up getting married within the time,
so that that money is no longer—that money is not necessary. The
moment the whole thing is paid out,
the יורשים yorshim have lost
the—right—they no longer—they don't have a
lien on that field anymore. That's correct.
That's correct. Literally he's doing it—it's sort of to do it retroactively.
In other words, you know, we know that if she waits too
long, she loses out. But if she waits—you know—what if she goes
just half a year, and if she has this—you know—the ability, she
has a little bit in her—her bank account—just half a year—and then
she sells the field and recoups what she sold, in which case
there's no issue with that at all? She hasn't gotten married yet.
Yeah, so there is—she could do it that way. We do discuss
the possibility of her taking
money—let's say—getting—getting a—a reimbursement for her מזונות. mezonos. But that seems not
to be the case that we're discussing.
No, I understand. I was saying—the other way you could have done
it.
Yes, she could have done it that way.
אמר אמימר. amar ameimar. אמימר ameimar says: הלכתא מוכרת לששה
חדשים ולוקח מפרנס אחת לשלושים יום.
hilchetha mocheres leshishe
chodoshim veloke'ach mefarnes achas lishloshim yom. I'm sorry, every time I read
through this, I keep on—my eyes keep on saying the wrong thing.
In any case, אמימר ameimar פסק pasken like רב יהודה. rav yehuda.
אמר ליה רב אשי לאמימר: amar lei rav ashi le'ameimar:
ורב הונא מאי? verav huna mai? Oh! Why? You chose—we have—we have
a statement of רב הונא, rav huna, who is the ראש ישיבה
rosh yeshiva of סורא. sura. We have a statement of רב יהודה,
rav yehuda, who is the ראש ישיבה rosh yeshiva of פומבדיתא. pumbedita.
They're contemporary. Neither one of them is more—particularly authoritative over the other.
And then we have a ברייתא baraisa in favor of both of
them. So why are you telling me this? אמר ליה לא שמיע
לי. amar lei lo shemi'a lei. I didn't hear it.
Which is interesting. You didn't know about רב הונא? rav huna? So
the גמרא—it's gemara not clear to me if it's the גמרא gemara
or if it's—if it's him himself saying: כלומר לא סבירא לי. kelomar
lo sevira lei. I don't agree with him. I don't agree with
him and so I פסק pasken like רב יהודה. rav yehuda. We're
not dealing with a—a פסק psak on the part in from a—an
authoritative source, but rather, I myself just simply think that the רב
יהודה's rav yehuda position is the
correct—the correct position.
לא שמיע לי. lo shemi'a lei. Mhmm. Shmeea is that—hear?
Yes, that's a fairly common thing for people to say in חז"ל.
chazal. Remember that everything is oral—is oral tradition. So if you don't
have a tradition, then you say: לא שמיע לי. lo shemi'a lei.
I have not heard that that is the case in הלכה. halacha.
The assumption here is that לא שמיע לי lo shemi'a lei is
not "I didn't know about it", but actually, "I don't agree with
it. I think that it's the wrong—the wrong answer."
The way we say in English: "I hear you," meaning "I understand,
I agree with you." Yeah, perhaps. Similar, similar.
בעו מיניה מרב ששת.
be'u
minei merav sheishes.
By the way, this is all hovering—all these conversations are—well, אמימר ameimar
and רב אשי rav ashi are different—but רב ששת rav sheishes is
around the same time as רב דניאל בר קטינא. rav daniel bar
katina. So we're kind of in this—in this similar place. בעו מיניה
מרב ששת: be'u minei merav sheishes: מוכרת למזונות מהו שתחזור ותטרוף
לכתובתה? mocheres lemezonos mahu shetachzor vetitrof lechesuvashah?
This is an interesting situation.
For מזונות, mezonos, if
we all—you're familiar with the case of liens. Somebody who has
a—somebody who—who loans money. By the way, this is something I do
with
my—students—go over this particular case in the—with the students in the ישיבה
yeshiva all the time. It's not an easy case to get a
hold of. But somebody who has
a—who takes a loan,
so the—everything that they own, all of their landed property, then becomes—land
that is on—that is mortgaged. If they sell that property in the
course of—the time before they're required to pay off their loan, and
then they default on their loan, the person who loaned them—them money,
their creditor, can go to the people who bought them—who bought the
property and say: "I'm sorry, this property is under lien. I'm going
to seize this property in order to pay off my loan. You're
going to have to work it out together." with the other person
about getting your money back.
This is also the case of a כתובה. Ketubah. A woman who,
when we write our כתובות, Ketubot, we say, you know, everything is
אחראין achrayin on this כתובה, Ketubah, even the גלימא דעל כתפאי—I'll gelima
de'al katfai make sure it's on camera—right, the coat that's on my
back, on a chair. In any case, the,
everything is considered to be on mortgage to this כתובה, Ketubah, and
therefore if when a husband dies or when they get divorced, the
husband is bankrupt, the wife can go to the people who he
has sold his property to in the last since they got married
and say, I'm sorry, this property comes to me, you're going to
need to work it out together with my husband, or with his
heirs, in order to get your money back. However, you cannot do
this for מזונות. mezonot. You can't seize property for מזונות. mezonot. So
here's an interesting case. She can sell property in order to get
the מזונות, mezonot, but she can't actually seize property for it. So
what happens?
The יורשין, yorshin, the inheritors are bankrupt. They can't give her מזונות,
mezonot, or anyway, they're not paying her מזונות. mezonot. So she takes
from their fields and she sells them, okay, to get the מזונות.
mezonot. Now at some point she decides that she's ready to receive
her כתובה Ketubah
and so she says, okay, give me my כתובה, Ketubah, and they
say, we don't have enough to cover it. Can she go back
and take that same field that she sold in order to get
מזונות mezonot and say, oh, I'm sorry,
now we have a debt, a lien,
this field was mortgaged, I'm going to need to take that to
pay off my כתובה, Ketubah, and you'll have to work out how
to get your money back with the יורשין. yorshin. The יורשין yorshin
weren't even the people who bought it, who sold it.
So we say קמיבעיא להו בדרב יוסף, kamibaya lehu bid'Rav Yosef, they're
actually asking a question about something that רב יוסף Rav Yosef himself
said. דאמר רב יוסף. da'amar Rav Yosef. רב יוסף Rav Yosef is
from the same time as רב ששת Rav Sheshet also. I don't
know if these little comments are of interest but they're of interest
to me. אלמנתא דזבנה אחריות איתמי
ובי דינא
דזבני אחריות איתמי. almantah dezabnah achrayut ayitmei u'vei dina dezabni achrayut ayitmei.
When a widow has to sell land, we
say that actually the אחריות achrayut for that land, that is to
say if that land then gets snatched up by a creditor,
the person you have to go back and discuss with how to
get your money back is the inheritors of the original, yes, that's
right, the heirs of the original owner.
So we say, so now, right, this is the question is, okay,
we've said that the אחריות achrayut is on the יתמי, yatmei, that
seems to suggest that a woman should be able to seize that
exact same land, right, because it's not really her responsibility. The responsibility
is as though the heirs sold off the land, and now she's
going just to collect more land. So we say what's going on
here? מאי כיון דאחריות איתמי טרפא? mai keivan de'achrayut ayitmei tarfa? Maybe
because the responsibility for paying the כתובה Ketubah off, not just the
כתובה Ketubah but the responsibility for this land, this mortgaged land and
how are you going to get your money back, etc., that falls
not on her but the responsibility for selling it falls not on
her but on the orphans.
Maybe she can take it because she's not a part of that
conversation. או דלמא מצו אמרי לה? o dilma matzu amri lah? Maybe
they can say to her, this is a great line, מנהי דאחריות
דעלמא לא קבלת עלך אחריות דנפשך מי לא קבלת? mineih de'achrayut de'alma
lo kabalt alach achrayut denafshach mi lo kabalt? All right, you have
not received
the responsibility for all of the debts that our father had over
the course of his life in general.
Did you not accept responsibility for the sales you yourself made? In
other words, look, we can understand that if you had to sell
something and then a creditor came and snatched up that property because
to pay a previous debt, it's our job to make good the
sale because it's our job to feed you. But you sold this
property and now you want to take it back in order for
it to be the כתובה? Ketubah? That's your business both times. Surely
you accept responsibility for that. If you wanted this land for your
כתובה Ketubah you shouldn't have sold it off in order to get
yourself מזונות. mezonot. I have to say, so then she'd say
well but then why didn't you give me anything?
So I'm actually sympathetic to the first argument, which is, you know,
like okay, they could say that to her and she could respond
to them well it has been your responsibility all along to provide
me with the things that I'm entitled to. If you don't do
it, then essentially I'm acting as an agent on your behalf until
I start acting on my own behalf.
What about the third party? I mean, when he goes into this,
this must have been a common situation.
I don't know how common. What I can tell you is that
even today when people buy property they get a, they go to
to. If you don't do it, then essentially I'm
acting as an agent on your behalf until I start acting on
my own behalf. What about the context? I mean, when he goes
into this, this must have been a common situation. I don't know
how common. What I can tell you is that even today when
people buy property, they go to property title search. To yeah, to
various... I don't mean that part of it. I'm sorry. I mean
in these circumstances where initially she's selling it for sustenance and he's
going through that procedure of giving her a monthly payment. He wouldn't
he also be aware wondering you know her situation and that this
might turn around?
So that's exactly what I'm referring to, which is that yes, you
go and you look for you do a tight what even today
when you're buying property, you make sure that there are no previous
claims on that property or you know that there are previous claims
which lowers the value of the property and you pay a little
less, right? So this is maybe a I mean a lot of
the things that we talk about especially with a כתובה ketubah woman
who sells her כתובה ketubah woman people who sell land that has
liens on them and so on, but people who are buying are
a kind of venture capitalists, they see an opportunity to buy low
and sell high under the expectation that this person, this you know,
this guy's restaurant is going to eventually take off and they'll be
able to pay off their loans and then the property will belong
to me and I bought it at a fraction of the cost.
That's what's happening here is that she's selling off land which is
heavily mortgaged,
and this buyer's takes knows that he he has a chance of
getting cheap land he takes the the chance that the land will
actually be repossessed depending on how good his lawyer is, you know,
he at any case has the right at least to go back
and ask for his money back from the original the people the
אחריות achrayut is on.
And then the question is can she be the one who repossesses
that land?
That's right. The same land that she originally sold. That's right. אמר
ליה, Amlei, this is now we're back to רב ששת Rav Sheshet
giving the answer. רב ששת Rav Sheshet said תני תנא, tni tua,
we have a משנה mishna that says this.
But she can potentially do this a number of times, right? Like
let's say the land was worth a hundred dollars and the כתובה
ketubah was five thousand dollars. Right. And then this guy buys it
and she repossesses it, and you know, and then he works it
out with them gets you have
ten guys right?
Like she does this again and again and again? So let's see...
like the same one, the same field?
I don't know that she could do the same field because once
she collects her כתובה, ketubah, at least according to what...
No, it may not be worth the full value of her כתובה.
ketubah.
Yes, but it's a little odd.
I mean somebody's going to get bit twice?
I mean
in classic Waxman style you are moving ahead to questions that the
גמרא Gemara is going to discuss in terms of
what is what does it mean when she's collect a collected a
part of her כתובה. ketubah. Does that mean that she has like
has she canceled her right to מזונות mezonot or has she not
canceled her right to מזונות? mezonot? So in classic Rezekoff style, I'm
going to just tell you that we'll wait and hear what they
have to say about that. You can see if it satisfies you
or not.
All right, תני תנא. tni tua. תני תנא, tni tua, he says
תני תנא, tni tua, we
have a we have a משנה mishna that says this: מוכרת והולכת
עד כדי כתובתה. mocheret ve'holechet ad kedei ketubtah.
That was a compliment by the way, I just wanted to make
clear that wasn't a... that wasn't a שטאָך. shtoch. Okay. אמר ליה
תני תנא, Amlei tni tua, it says we have a משנה, mishna,
מוכרת והולכת עד כדי כתובתה. mocheret ve'holechet ad kedei ketubtah. She can
continue to sell our fields for the purpose of her... of her
מזונות mezonot until there's only enough field left to pay off her
כתובה. ketubah. וסמך לה שתגבה כתובתה מן השאר. V'samach lah shetigbeh ketubtah
min hashar.
And we rely on her or they rely on... I'm not sure
who the סמך samach is I have to say it, I feel
like it should say סמכה. samcha. In any case,
but it is relied upon her that she will collect her כתובה
ketubah from the remaining field that she's left behind. So maybe we
empower her legally to then... yes, the personal... the personal
conjugation here is puzzling to me. It is a masculine singular. I
cannot figure out who the masculine singular is. בית דין Beitin maybe?
בית דין Beitin
it should usually also סמכו. samchu. Okay. It's just not clear to
me. In any case, שמע מינה שיירה אין לא שיירה לא. shema
mina, shayra in, la shayra la. If she has properties left over
then she receives then she is permitted to... to collect this money
to take... to have this כתובה. ketubah. If she didn't, then those
properties are gone. Meaning essentially the second that she cannot receive her
כתובה ketubah from the same properties that she has sold off. So
we say ודלמא עצה טובה קמשמע לן? v'dilma etza tova kamashmalan? Maybe
they're actually just giving us good advice that that's the way she
should best... she should do it so she doesn't get into complicated
issues.
דלא ליקרו לה הגומיתא, d'la likru lah hagomita, so people won't say
oh, she's an unreliable, right? She gets
low ratings on eBay, right? That people will say oh, she doubles
back on you.
So he says this is another version of עצה טובה. etza tova.
Yesterday we had that...
yeah, there was עצה טובה דרבנותא. etza tova d'rabnutah. That's right. That's
right. So we say אם כן ליתא גובה כתובתה מן השאר מאי
סמך לה? im ken leita, govah ketubtah min hashar, mai samach lah?
שמע מינה שיירה אין לא שיירה לא. shema mina, shayra in, la
shayra la.
So if it was the case it was just עצה טובה, Etzah
Tovah, good-good advice that we were giving her, then we would have
said
that it should have said, "and she collects her ketubah from the
rest." What does it mean that she relies on the rest to
collect her ketubah? Or we rely—again, not clear to me who this
סמך samach refers to. In any case, that word סמך לה samach
la indicates that if she leaves it over, she can collect her
ketubah. If she doesn't leave it over, she's stuck.
איבעיא להו. ibaya lehu. They asked the question: זבנה דלא איצטריכו ליה—לא
איצטריכו ליה—זוזי, ולא איצטריכו ליה זוזי,
velo itztrichu lei
zuzi, הדרי זביני או לא הדרי זביני. hadrey zvini o lo hadrey
zvini. Somebody who sells property, this is in the course of—this is
in the along the context of a woman who sells property in
order to get her מזונות mezonot and then gets married or something
like that. So now we ask the general question: If you sell
property and you no longer need the money that you thought you
needed, can you say, "Oh, I'm taking it back"?
This is בעל כרחו. be'al korcho.
This is not—not בעל כרחו. be'al korcho. Somebody who simply sells off
their property in order to get money to—well, we'll see, there are
lots of examples here that we're going to see in a minute.
But they no longer need it. They did it for the purpose
of getting money; they no longer need it. So we say, but
how could he know
that this is my property? I just, you know, just want a
little bit of cash flow and then they say, "Oh, I didn't
realize it's worth a million dollars, I only needed a hundred thousand
dollars." I can go back to the purchaser?
It's not so much I didn't—it's not that I only needed this
and I didn't need as much money as the property got me.
It's more like—well, let's—let's hear the examples and we'll go back, okay?
תא שמע. ta shema. דההוא גברא דזבין ארעא לרב פפא דאיצטריכו ליה
זוזי למזבן תורי. deha'hu gavra d'zavin ara l'Rav Pappa d'itzrichu lei zuzi
limzban tore. There was a man who needed oxen in order to
plow his land. He didn't have livestock. Without livestock, land is not
worth very much in the ancient days. I guess it's a little
like today if you don't have the—the—the machinery that you need; you
need a tractor in order to plow your field.
Okay, but if you buy land in New York City, it'd be
worth a lot, you could just—people just hold on and let it
appreciate.
Okay, so if you buy land in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, if
you don't have what to—what to use it for, you're going to
just—it's going to just sit there fallow and it's not going to
really
be—this is—this is—this is—this is סתם, stum, however you pronounce this word.
You know, what—you know, with—with—you know, with—you know, what—would be—would be—would be
a fact, right? If I said, "I'm selling for this
purpose," versus me saying it just סתם. stum. So okay, but he
is selling it סתם. stum. Okay, that's important here. You're right. But
if you say, "I'm selling it for the purpose," maybe we can
say afterwards what was a מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. In any case,
he needs—he needs oxen in order to buy this property. So what
happens? He sells off a small portion of his land to Rav
Pappa. לסוף לא איצטריכו
ליה. lesof lo itztrichu lei. It turns out that oxen are cheaper
than he thought. Not that he got more land than he expected—no,
more for the land than he expected, but that he actually realized,
"Oh, I actually had money that I could have used for the
oxen." אהדריה
ניהליה רב פפא לארעיה. ahadrei nihalei Rav Pappa l'arei. And Rav Pappa
returns his land.
Kind of—it's not—it's—now—now...
so Michael says, anticipating the גמרא, Gemara, wait, wait, wait.
He does this out of the goodness of his heart?
He's paying to get back the land. So if he—if one does—if
they—if we say it goes—the land goes back, you—the—I mean, even in
the case of Rav Pappa, he gave back the land and took
back his money. He doesn't take a loss. He says, "Oh, you
didn't need the money? Okay, here's your land back and you can
keep the money." Right? You always get your—you always get your money
back. But what you said about the goodness of your heart is
exactly the point that the גמרא Gemara makes next. The גמרא Gemara
says, רב פפא לפנים משורת הדין הוא דעבד. Rav Pappa lifnim mishurat
hadin hu de'avad. Rav Pappa is a צדיק. tzadik.
He sees that this fellow sold off some of his land in
order to get a certain amount of money, but he didn't need
the money, and Rav Pappa said, "Look, I'm not going to hold
you to it. You know, here's your land, you give me back
my money."
Yeah, that of course doesn't answer the question.
So it doesn't answer the question. That's right. That was unusual. Right.
תא שמע. ta shema. This is just a very interesting economic situation.
דההוא בצורתא דהוה בנהרדעא. deha'hu betzorta de'hava b'Nahardea.
There was a local famine in נהרדעא. Nahardea. How does a local
famine happen? So רשי Rashi explains that the river rises, it's too
difficult to get boats when the river is wild or something; it's
hard to get boats over. And so the price of wheat goes
way up as the shipments from outside of נהרדעא Nahardea start to
become difficult. זבינו כולי עלמא לאפדנייהו. zvinu kulei alma l'afdanaihu. Everybody starts
selling off
their אפדנא—אפדנא is like a—is a mansion. But presumably people are selling
off their homes in order to be able to pay for food.
לסוף אתו חטי. lesof atu chiti. But eventually the boats did come
in. As soon as the boats come in, of course, this
artificial—I don't know—the—it was a bubble. Right. Right. It
crashes. Right. Eventually, this artificial situation where the—the—the prices go up, exactly,
immediately crashes and all the—and all the wheat goes down again. Now
in this It happened before everybody needed it in order to or
starve. אמר ליה רב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Nachman, Rav Nachman said,
דינא הוא דהדרי אפדני למרייהו. Dina hu d'hadrei apadnei l'marihu. It makes
sense that we return all of these houses, these mansions, back to
the original owners. So the גמרא Gemara says, התם נמי זביני בטעות
הוו דאיגלאי מילתא דארבא בכילי הוה קיימא. Hatam nami zvinei b'ta'ut havu
d'iglai milta d'arba b'kilei havah kayma. And my S3 says, yeah, but
this is a מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. Everybody knows that these people
are selling off their property in order to get food. When the
truth is, if they only knew that the boats are just in
the next bay waiting for the river to go down low enough
for them to get around and dock in נהרדעא, Neharde'a, nobody would
be selling off their houses. It's just based
on a lack of information. I would point out that רש״י Rashi
then points out a couple of situations which would not be a
lack of situation. It seems that in those cases, your money would
not go, your mansion would not go back to you. In other
words, let's say that it's not that the boats were just around
the corner. It's that somehow somebody happened to have a load of
wheat that they were drawing from a place of
surplus. You know, the wheat prices there were too low. They show
up and flood the market with wheat in נהרדעא. Neharde'a. Nobody could
have expected it. רש״י Rashi says in that case רב פפא Rav
Papa would say, oh no, your houses are sold. Nobody could have
anticipated that and therefore it's not a מקח
טעות. mekach
ta'ut.
Says the גמרא, Gemara, אי הכי? I hachi?
I'm sorry, I'm still trying to understand this a little better. I
mean, it was obviously a wild river so they never thought that
the river is going to at some point subside and wheat's going
to come?
They did think. Sorry, they did not know how long it was
going to take for the wheat to get there.
Well, that's the whole point.
Nobody knows. So if they had known the boats were around the
corner, they would have waited more patiently.
They would have waited more patiently. Maybe not. Maybe it's look, this
river's been raging for three weeks. I don't care that the boats
are around. I need to eat now.
Okay, but you could make the argument that at the end of
the day רב נחמן Rav Nachman said the things return, the houses
return and the גמרא Gemara says that's because איגלאי מילתא. iglai milta.
It turns out that the boats were
there and you know, it was something that they could have known
and just didn't know. And רש״י Rashi says it's opposed to something
that really is something that nobody could have known, totally unexpected.
It's not something you could have known. That's the way business is
always conducted where it's just right around the corner.
Charlie. The
agriculture in Mesopotamia until 1258 was entirely based in irrigated agriculture.
So
this must have been a situation like the drought we have in
California right now, there was no water from the source of the
irrigation water.
I just don't know.
So
you don't think it was a wild river? I think it's the
opposite way.
Yeah, probably too little water. Could be.
I mean yeah.
So they had to import food? Yes, something.
If we say אי הכי, I hachi, if this is the case,
that really
it was this sort of unusual case where if they'd only known,
היינו דאמר רמי בר שמואל לרב נחמן אם כן נמצאת מכשילן לעתיד
לבוא.
Hainu d'amar Rami bar Shmuel l'Rav Nachman im ken nimtzeit
machshilan l'atid lavo. If you set things up this way, you're going
to end up not allowing people to sell off properties in the
next time there's an artificial dearth because what's going to happen? They're
going to say well, there might be boats just in the next
bay over, no buyer's going to go and do this and people
are going to have a hard time. אמר ליה אטו כל יומא
בצורתא שכיחא? Amar lei atu kol yoma batzoreta shchicha? Does it happen
so frequently that we have these artificial dearths? אמר ליה אין בצורתא
בנהרדעא מישכח שכיחא. Amar lei in batzoreta b'Neharde'a mishkach shchicha. It does
in fact happen that in נהרדעא, Neharde'a, yes, we get for some
reason something about the geography of נהרדעא Neharde'a is hard to get
the wheat in. והלכתא, V'hilchata, now he just gets the הלכה halacha
for the last word, זבין ולא אצטריכו ליה זוזי הדר זבינא. Zvin
v'la itztrichu lei zuzie hadar zvina. At the end of the day,
despite the fact that we were unable to prove it with examples,
if you sell something and it turns out that you don't need
the money, the business there, you can rescind it. I want to
do business. I honestly would want to do business with these kind
of people. They have ethics. I guess so. I mean, at the
end of the day, I see the two of you, at the
end of the day there is a lot of רחמנות rachmanut for
people who are selling off their property. I mean, but you didn't
stipulate anything. You didn't say why. I could be some guy from
the outside. I understand. I just have to remind you what it
means for people. Like, we're not in the time of the תנ״ך
Tanach where people have an אחוזה, achuzah, where it's like actually taking
a chunk of your body in order to sell off your land.
But land really meant something to people, and it was extremely painful
to sell off land. Is it just land? Or what if he
sold מטלטלין? metaltelin? Then what? I can't imagine that this is about
מטלטלין. metaltelin. This is about... No, I'm saying, meaning is there a
different דין din for מטלטלין? metaltelin? If I sold my car then
like, you know, really... I didn't... I didn't check, but it's very
hard for me to imagine that because people can take מטלטלין, metaltelin,
it could be anywhere. I don't... it seems unlikely to me, but
I can't say for sure. רב דב Rav Dov mentioned what I
was going to say, in other words, it must be something very
different than my going to a store, buying a product, coming back
the next day and saying, you know, I really don't need it
and I want to return it. That's like a no return, like
land seems to be different. Yeah, especially if I used it, you
know, use your furniture, oh, you know... I didn't mean... Charlie, that
last הלכתא hilchata seems feels like a post-Amoraic addition because it comes
out of nowhere. הלכתא hilchata is always a post-Amoraic addition, I'll just
throw that in. הלכתא hilchata is something that רב שרירא גאון, Rav
Sherira Gaon, for those of you who are familiar sort of with
the history of Talmudic sort of the generations of the Talmud, much
of that comes from a letter that רב שרירא גאון, Rav Sherira
Gaon, who was the ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, oh man, I'm just
going to choose one and hope that it's right, I'm pretty sure
that he was the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva of סורא, Sura, he
wrote to the community of Kairouan, North Africa, and one among the
things that they asked him was what is the position of... one
of the things they asked him was when was the משנה, Mishna,
why did רבי Rebbi actually write down the משנה? Mishna? And he
wrote back to them and said, רבי Rebbi never wrote down the
משנה, Mishna, I don't know what you're talking about, which something that
is ignored in many situations. The other thing he said is, so
then the other thing they asked him is what is the position
of the people who we call רבנן סבוראי? Rabanan Savorai? And without
this letter, it's likely we wouldn't actually know about רבנן סבוראי. Rabanan
Savorai. But he said, oh, רבנן סבוראי, Rabanan Savorai, those are the
people who after the אמוראים Amoraim came and made סדר seder and
actually gave the הלכתאs hilchata at the end of סוגיות sugyot to
tell us what the actual הלכה halacha is. So yes, I agree
with you, הלכתא hilchata is almost always an addition of רבנן סבוראי.
Rabanan Savorai. Yes, what's your question? So I just want to make
sure, like again, this is kind of a case, because I raised
whether you expressed your reasoning for the sale, does that make a
difference or not? So it appears not, it appears not. Because it
seemed, the reason I said let's wait and see is because this
case of the אפתנא, apatna, the mansions, seemed to be a case
where everybody knew that they were selling off the money for food
because they couldn't get any food. And therefore it was a מקח
טעות, mekach taut, which didn't prove that you can... But it has
to be אומדנא, umdena, in other words, like in other words, the
whole town is selling it, but in this case I'm just selling
it. Correct. So it sounds like this is the argument we're making
here is not an argument of מקח טעות. mekach taut. The argument
we're making here is, no, I sold it, it turned out that
I didn't need the money and so I can go back. I
don't need to say I'm buying it for this purpose, selling it
for this purpose, and then you find out that that purpose no
longer exists. I expect that there might be, you know, at some
point somebody might put some measures in place in order to protect
people from lies. Oh actually, absolutely, look look right here, כגון שגילה
דעתו בשעת המכר, kegon she-gilah da'ato b'sha'at ha-mecher, דאמרינן דאי הוה ידעינן
דהכי הוי לא הוה מזבין ליה, damrinan d'ee hava yadinan d'hachi hava
lo hava mezavin leh, דברים שבלב. devarim she-be-lev. Oh, there you go.
That's odd to me because it seems like this is in contrast
to what's it called, to a מקח טעות. mekach taut. Yes. So
am I wrong in suggesting that this implies that there's a basic
expectation of decency amongst people, that if you're so desperate that you're
selling your land to survive, buy food to survive, that when that
is no longer an
issue, the people who purchased the land have the רחמנות rachmonus to
say, we understand, this is fundamental to you? I'm not sure that
that's the, that is to say, that would be nice, but that
seems to be, they seem to attribute that to רב פפא. Rav
Pappa. That seems to be לפנים משורת הדין, lifnim mishurat hadin, this
seems to be שורת הדין. shurat hadin. The law is, it's not
that you have רחמנות, rachmonus, it's that we make you return it,
that somebody can take you to בית דין Beit Din and say
you don't want to return it but you have to. That's the
rule. The rule is I sold it for money, I don't need
the money, here's your money, take it back, I want my land
back. And the reason for the rule seems to be רחמנות rachmonus
on the part of legislated רחמנות. rachmonus. Yeah, exactly. Yes, that's correct.
Do you think another question is like do you reimburse for like
your business costs, like you know, or is it just the cost
of buying it? Like, you know, I had to engage a lawyer
to draw up the contract and now the whole thing is worthless.
Does it say this is another different mindset? Yeah, I mean I
think that Michael has demonstrated that pretty convincingly. מתניתין *Matnitin*. אלמנה בין
מן האירוסין בין מן הנישואין *Almana bein min hairusin bein min hanisuin*
מוכרת שלא בבית דין din *mocheret shelo b'veit din*. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon. אומר אומר *Rabbi Shimon omer omer* מן הנישואין מוכרת שלא בבית
דין *min hanisuin mocheret shelo b'veit din* מן האירוסין לא תמכור אלא
בבית דין min ha'erusin lo timkor ella be'veit din. *min hairusin lo
timkor ela b'veit din*. What do you need to do in order
to sell off properties that belong to these יורשים yorshim *yorshim*? Can
you just, you know, put up a sign for sale by owner
and then and go ahead and make that sale even though you're
not really the owner? Or do you have to go through some
kind of legal process? So, the תנא קמא *Tanna Kama* says a
a widow can in fact go through the process even though she's
not actually the she's not actually the owner. She doesn't need to
go through בית דין beit din. *Beit Din*. What does that mean
exactly? Is it she has to tell them? I presume that she
needs to, I mean, the truth is I'm not sure what exactly
it's about and רש"י *Rashi* doesn't say. But my expectation is that
she is doing it בית דין beit din, *Beit Din* is doing
it for her, she is doing it מכוח בית דין beit din
*mikoach Beit Din*, something there's that she has somehow made official gone
to through official channels in order to place this property. So, they
say whether she is a widow from actual marriage or she's just
a widow from engagement, that is to say she got engaged and
her husband died, she can sell off property. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon,
*Rabbi Shimon* says no. She can sell off property if she's a
widow from marriage, but from engagement she can't without going to בית
דין beit din. *Beit Din*. Except unless she goes to בית דין
beit din *Beit Din* מפני שאין לה מזונות *mipnei she'ein la mezonot*.
She doesn't have a right to food. Then why is she selling
it at all? Selling for her כתובה ktubah. *ketubah*. Right? There are
two situations here. One is a woman who gets married who actually
gets married, when her husband dies has a right to be fed
until the time that she gets remarried. We saw in the מסכתא
*Masechta* when we learned them. And and that includes that's food and
eventually she also will get a כתובה *ketubah*. And so she's permitted,
according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon: *Rabbi Shimon*, she's permitted to sell
off whenever because she has this constant need for sustenance, assuming that
the יורשים yoshim *yorshim* are not giving her what she needs. But
a woman who is only widowed from from engagement, in that case,
she is she doesn't have the right to to sustenance. She only
has the right to a כתובה *ketubah*. And such, רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon* says וכל שאין לה מזונות לא תמכור אלא בבית דין *ve'chol
she'ein la mezonot lo timkor ela b'veit din*. Somebody who doesn't have
the right to a to this regular income does not sell without
the official sanction of the בית דין *Beit Din*. The גמרא *Gemara*
says בשלמא מן הנישואין משום מזוני אלא מן האירוסין מאי טעמא *bishlama
min hanisuin mishum mazonei ela min hairusin mai taama*. So we say,
okay, I can understand why תנא קמא *Tanna Kama* would permit a
woman from the from marriage to sell off land without going to
בית דין *Beit Din* because she needs this the food, the same
as רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*.
But somebody who's
widowed just
from engagement, why should we allow her to do this without official
sanction? אמר עולא משום חינא *Amar Ulla mishum china*. עולא *Ulla* said
it's because of חן chen *chen*. Now there's a מחלוקת *machloket* here
between רש"י *Rashi* and the תוספות *Tosafot* exactly what what חן chen.
*chen* means in this case, sort of grace. רש"י *Rashi* says we'd
like for her to have a pleasant memory of her husband. חנא
*China* in רש"י *Rashi* שיהיו בעליהן לחן בעיניהן *sheyiheyu ba'aleihen lechen be'eineihen*.
Their husbands will be it'll be pleasant for them, a pleasant memory.
ולא ימנעו נשים מלינשא לאנשים *velo yimne'u nashim milinsa la'anashim*. And women
won't say, oh, such a headache to get my כתובה *ketubah* when
I get widowed, I don't want to get back into this situation
again. It gets a little difficult to understand that in the continuation.
רש"י *Rashi* had daughters? Perhaps. I don't know. Perhaps that's רש"י'ס *Rashi's*
motivation. In any case, the תוספות *Tosafot* go in a totally different
direction when it starts gets complicated. That's when all that's when I'll
bring it up. So, for now though, we can understand it that
way. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר *Rabbi Yochanan amar* לפי שאין אדם
רוצה שתתבזה אשתו בבית דין *lefi she'ein adam rotze shetitbaze ishto b'veit
din*. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says no. The reason is that nobody
really wants their wife to have to go to בית דין *Beit
Din* and say it's an uncomfortable situation. Charlie? There's a great שפת
אמת'ס *Sfat Emes's* comment here. רש"י'ס *Rashi's* opinion not only does רש"י'ס
*Rashi's* opinion not go with the גמרא *Gemara* here, it stands in
contradiction to a previous גמרא *Gemara* about two weeks ago that states
women want to be married more than men wish to marry them.
Okay, yes, I mean, that is a that is a statement in
the גמרא *Gemara*. And that doesn't seem to me that it's so
much in contradiction to that particular statement, but it is difficult in
the continuation. We'll see how. In any case, the there has been
a constant theme. I don't know if you've noticed or if Rabbi
Winzer has mentioned over the course of the time that you've been
learning כתובות *Ketubot*, that there is a sense in
כתובות
*Ketubot* that...
It's a בזיון
for
men that
if their daughters should go בחזרות על הפתחים bichozrot al haptachim if
they have to go begging for food. There's a kind of sense
that men want proper decorum.
So
I'm not really
sure how
to interpret this sort of along a feminist line. In any case,
we say מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what would be the difference between
them? איכא בינייהו גרושה, ika beinaihu grushah, right? The excluded middle as
Rabbi Winzer would say, the divorcee who we haven't mentioned. למאן דאמר
משום חינא, leman de'amar mishum china, the one who says it's because
we want her to have a, whatever it is that חן chen
is, גרושה נמי בעיא חן. grushah nami ba'ya chen. A גרושה grushah
also needs to have חן. chen למאן דאמר לפי שאין אדם רוצה
שתתבזה אשתו בבית דין, leman de'amar lefi she'ein adam rotzeh she'titpazeh ishto
be'veit din, but the one who says a man doesn't want his
wife to have to go out into the public sphere or be
embarrassing for her, גרושה מאי איכפת ליה? grushah mai ikpat leh? Right?
A man with a relationship with his wife is not such a
problem. So here רש״י Rashi explains why does the גרושה grushah need
to have sort of pleasant memory? Somehow, in order to she wants
to get remarried. Right? In order to encourage her to get remarried
we have to let her know how easy it is to get
her needs met or something like that. So but the one who
says it's about not wanting your wife to be embarrassed, so then
that doesn't make sense with the גרושה. grushah. Charlie? Yeah, I wonder
how much this was the status at the time, particularly in areas
that were under control of Rome. In Roman society, relationships between men
and women were not accepted. I mean men would take other people's
wives on a regular basis. And רבי יוחנן lived in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. I wonder if that social fact might have affected some
of the opinions there. It could be although we certainly have seen
Babylonian positions that also have a similar situation. I don't know what
things were like in Persian rule. I mean I think as you
go back into pre-modern times, I think that there is a much,
I mean it's fairly recent that women have sort of come out
into the public sphere. רב דב? Rav Dov? Yeah, just the חן
chen here according to רש״י Rashi is that if someone who was
engaged she'd be given this amount so that she would in the
future go into a future marriage feeling good about it. Not so
clear to me what the story, yeah, something like that. That they
have some kind of positive experience of marriage even though it wasn't
consummated so that she will be able to go into a future
marriage, something like that. תנן. Tnan. So once we've said that the
difference is a גרושה, grushah, we have a משנה, Mishnah, the very
next משנה Mishnah that we're going to see: וגרושה לא תמכור אלא
בבית דין. ve'grushah lo timkor ella be'veit din. When we say, oh,
we actually have a דין that tells us exactly what's going on
here. That a divorcee has to do it from בית דין. So
what does that suggest? If she needs to do it in בית
דין, that suggests that the argument of חן chen doesn't make sense
here. It must be the argument of שלא תתבזה אשתו בבית דין.
she'lo titpazeh ishto be'veit din. Right? That should teach us. So we
say בשלמא למאן דאמר לפי שאין אדם רוצה שתתבזה אשתו בבית דין,
bishlama leman de'amar lefi she'ein adam rotzeh she'titpazeh ishto be'veit din, גרושה
לא איכפת ליה. grushah lo ikpat leh. Okay, it makes sense that
we make a גרושה grushah go to בית דין according to that
person. אלא למאן דאמר משום חינא, ella leman de'amar mishum china, גרושה
נמי בעיא חן. grushah nami ba'ya chen. A divorcee of all people
we need to encourage that this is an easy process and she
should get into it. So we say הא מני רבי שמעון היא.
ha mani Rabbi Shimon hi. Oh, this last piece, this is actually
רבי שמעון. So we say רבי שמעון, היא רבי שמעון, hi Rabbi
Shimon, הא תנא ליה רישא. ha tana leh reisha. We already have
a statement of רבי שמעון: מן האירוסין לא תמכור אלא בבית דין.
We know that a woman from an engagement point of view doesn't
can't sell unless she actually goes to בית דין. Why should a
גרושה grushah be any different? So we say מהו דתימא, mahu detema,
what might we think? אלמנה מן האירוסין הוא דלא נפיש לחינא דידה.
almanah min ha'erusin hu dela nafshuh lechen ddidah. The a widow from
engagement has to go to בית דין because she doesn't have much
חן chen and this is where רש״י Rashi's interpretation starts to fall
apart. Why is her חן less? So רש״י Rashi says, well, she
wasn't that attached to her husband in the first place and so
it's not like she's going to feel like things are really bad
or something like that. אבל גרושה דנפיש חינה דידה, aval grushah de'nafshuh
chen ddidah, but a גרושה grushah who does have a lot of
חן because she was actually involved in a real relationship, אימא. eima.
Maybe she actually does need חן *chen*. So here's where we go
to the תוספות *Tosafot* and just see that רבינו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chanana*
has a different interpretation of this whole thing. We say גרושה *grusha*,
what was? פירש רבינו חננאל *peresh Rabbeinu Chananel* second line in that
תוספות *Tosafot*, גרושה נפיש חן דידה דיש לה תוספת *grusha nafish chen
didah de-yesh la tosefet*. For a גרושה *grusha* we have to she
has more חן *chen*. What exactly is that חן *chen*? She has
a תוספת *tosefet*, an additional get money from the husband. So you're
saying חן *chen* means money? Apparently. But then she man had everything
then how big the because the ארוסה *arusa* is still... Okay so
wait a second. והואיל ויש לה לגבות כל כך אימא שתמכור שלא
בבית דין *ve-ho'il ve-yesh la ligvot kol kach eima she-timkor she-lo be-veit
din*. Right she has a large amount of money that she really
is owed, whereas an ארוסה *arusa* doesn't normally receive the תוספת *tosefet*.
Well that just depends on what the כתובה *ketuba* was. You shouldn't
make you shouldn't wholesale this thing that she wouldn't receive... Okay so
ואישה שיש לה כתובתה הרבה *ve-isha she-yesh la ketubata arbeh* or whatever.
I will say that רבינו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chanana*'s next example is a
little... next suggestion is a little bit better. אי נמי יש לפרש
שהיא צריכה חן יותר מן הש... שהיא בזויה יותר מן האלמנה *i
nami yesh le-pharesh she-hi tzericha chen yoter min ha-she... she-hi bzuya yoter
min ha-almana*. All right? A גרושה *grusha* is actually in socially in
a more difficult position. More vulnerable position. Yeah more vulnerable position, a
more socially unpleasant position. Right? People are not as sympathetic for a
woman who is... for a divorcee as they are for a widow.
That being the case, we need to make this process easier for
her rather than harder. So you're saying נפיש חן דידה *nafish chen
didah* meaning she needs more חן *chen*, not that she has more?
Yes, something like that. Yeah. I mean in both of those cases,
right, נפיש חן דידה *nafish chen didah* meaning she has more need
if she has the תוספת *tosefet* also. Yes. So short question. So
I thought this משנה *Mishna* was clearly a continuation of the previous
סוגיא *sugya*. But I just need clarification. רש״י *Rashi*, the first רש״י
*Rashi* on this משנה *Mishna*, says שאין לה מזונות ומוכרת לכתובתה *she-ein
la mezonot u-mocheret le-ketubata*. Is she selling the land for מזונות *mezonot*
or she's selling for עיקר כתובה *ikar ketuba*? That's for the... a
woman who is... מעיקר האירוסין *me-ikar ha-erusin* who has no מזונות *mezonot*
and therefore she sells. Okay good, thank you. And in תוספות *Tosafot*,
when תוספות *Tosafot* says אי נמי *i nami*, should I understand that
the second... after the אי נמי *i nami* is also רבינו חננאל
*Rabbeinu Chanana*? I think the תוספות *Tosafot* themselves. I think that's רבינו
חננאל *Rabbeinu Chanana*, otherwise I think they would have made a note
of it. Yeah. Okay. I didn't check in רבינו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chanana*
himself. So we say, if you were to think that, right, that
actually רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* would have this argument that a גרושה
*grusha* actually needs more חן *chen* and therefore she should be able
to do without בית דין *beit din*... we say hold on a
second... so we say הא נמי תנינא *ha nami tninan*, we have
a משנה *Mishna* that talks about this as well. כל שאין לה
מזונות *kol she-ein la mezonot*, any woman who doesn't get מזונות *mezonot*
doesn't do it except for... has to go to בית דין *beit
din* in order to sell. לאתויי מאי *le-atuyei mai*? Who are we
talking about? לאו לאתויי גרושה *lav le-atuyei grusha*? Aren't we talking about
a גרושה *grusha*? Right? That's... so we say לא לאתויי מגורשת ואינה
מגורשת *lo le-atuyei megureshet ve-eina megureshet*. A woman who's in a ספק
*safek*. Her husband threw a כתובה *ketuba* at her... sorry, a גט
*get* at her in רשות הרבים *reshut ha-rabim*. We're not sure who
it was closer to. Was it closer to her, in which case
she's divorced, or was it closer to him, in which case she's
not divorced? In those cases, we're not sure what to do. כדרבי
זירא דאמר רבי זירא כל מקום שאמרו מגורשת ואינה מגורשת *ki-de-Rabbi Zeira
de-amar Rabbi Zeira kol makom she-amru megureshet ve-eina megureshet*... בעל חייב במזונותיה
*ba'al chayav bi-mezonoteiha*. Right? The husband is חייב במזונותיה *chayav bi-mezonoteiha*. בעל
חייב במזונותיה *ba'al chayav bi-mezonoteiha* says רש״י *Rashi*, but once he's dead,
then the יורשים yorshim, *yorshim* are not. Only the בעל בחיים *ba'al
ba-chayayim*. תא שמע *ta shema*. So now we're going to continue to
try to figure out, okay, so can we solve this question about
whether it's... both sides have answers for this issue. תא שמע כשם
שמוכרת שלא בבית דין כך יורשיה יורשי כתובתה מוכרין שלא בבית דין
*ta shema ke-shem she-mocheret she-lo be-veit din kach yorsheha yorshei ketubata mocherin
she-lo be-veit din*. The same way that she can sell out of
בית דין *beit din*, so similarly, the people who inherit her, or
her... are the people who inherit her כתובה *ketuba*, also can sell
outside of בית דין *beit din*. So we say, hmm, that's interesting.
Usually, who are the people who inherit her כתובה *ketuba*? We've seen
this now a couple of times. It's usually her sons, right, בנין
דכרין *banin dichrin*. So we say, so that's interesting. בשלמא למן דאמר
לפי שאין אדם רוצה שתתבזה אשתו בבית דין כי היכי דאילי דניחא
ליה דתתבזה יורשי נמי דניחא ליה דליבזו *bishlama le-man de-amar le-fi she-ein
adam rotze she-titbazye ishto be-veit din ki heichi de-i'lei de-nicha lei de-titbazye
yorshei nami de-nicha lei de-libazu*. This is interesting. So we say, oh,
if it's an issue of not having בזיון *bizayon*, it's actually a
בזיון *bizayon* not just for women in particular—maybe this is my feminist
read I'm looking for—right, it's actually a בזיון *bizayon* for anybody. In
the same way he doesn't want his wife going to בית דין
*beit din*, he doesn't want his יורשים *yorshim* going to בית דין
*beit din* either. It's just... It's just פשוטע פשטנות to be going
in and having to haggle over money with the court. אלא למאן
דאמר משום חינא, Ela l'man d'amar mishum china, but the person who
says it's in order to help her get remarried or to make
sure that she gets what she needs, sort of smooth out the
process, יורשים מאי חינא, mai china, right? The people who are who
the the יורשים are men, they aren't they aren't they don't need
extra help. תרגמה עולא כגון שירשתה בתה או אחותה, Tirgma Ula k'gon
she-yirshata bitah o afuta, right? It is the case where her her
daughter or her sister inherit her, which brings us back to it's
not actually בנין דיכרין benin dichrin that's going on here, right? The
husband died first. Usually בנין דיכרין benin dichrin is when the mother
the wife dies first and the husband dies second. In this case,
she could have any kind of יורשים, right? And they would also
be יורש yoresh כתובה. Okay, it is 8:35, 8:35. I guess I'll
stop here and thank you very much. Right, here we're doing daughters,
I have no sons. I have no sons.